This question's like kind of in a side,
but you mentioned uh before trying to
vet what an asset says to make sure that
they're they are doing exactly as they
say, and of course that the information
that they're giving you is true if
that's the case, but
is there operations officers that lie
about the intelligence that they get to
build a career for themselves?
>> Oh my god, we spent so much time on that
in in training. The The answer is yes,
unfortunately.
Um that leads to a very quick firing.
Um there are two things that case
officers
There are three things that case
officers sometimes
are caught doing.
Sometimes you will work for a total
[__]
who says
everybody needs to get five pieces of
finished intelligence or you don't meet
um threshold.
Okay, well some months I'm going to get
like 10 or 12, and some months I'm
cultivating new agents and I'm not going
to get any.
And they're not saying you need to
average five a month, you need five a
month.
So what that does is it encourages
people to just make the [__] up
and write it up as intelligence. Maybe
they'll pull it out of some obscure
newspaper,
which happens,
or
you have a meeting with an agent, he
gives you a
a a an amazing plethora of intelligence
reports,
and you just keep five in reserve for
next month.
If it's not too terribly time sensitive,
you give him the five that they need
right now, you save the next five for
next month. That's intellectually
dishonest.
And another one that people get caught
doing, and this is something I never
ever understood.
Depending on the station chief,
you're allowed to spend like up to five
bucks at a at a cover stop, an SDR cover
stop,
all the way up to 20 bucks at each cover
stop. It just depends on who happens to
be the chief.
Well, sometimes people will make up
receipts
or they'll save receipts and then just
put the money in their pockets.
So, what would possess you
to try to steal $20 from the CIA?
Is that really Is it worth being fired
to steal $20 from the CIA? I just never
understood it.
>> Well, does that say something about the
personality type that's recruited for
case officers?
>> Yes.
Yeah, that's exactly what it is.
You know,
we got
I I was in one assignment and and there
was some big
like senior senior enemy
leader
coming.
We heard he was staying in this hotel.
It was like a boutique hotel.
It had a bar in the in the lobby and he
was bringing in this giant contingent of
intelligence officers
with him to protect him.
So,
our boss said,
"You know, if you if you want to
try to get in on this, you should go to
the bar because we heard that these guys
are hanging out at the bar."
I'm like, "I I really don't want to go.
It's not my area of expertise. I don't
speak the language. I don't really care
about this country."
And um
and my wife, who is also a CIA officer,
said, "No, you really should go. You
know how they are. If you don't go,
they're going to criticize you."
So, I go. The bar was smaller than I
expected it to be, but literally every
seat
was taken by a CIA officer.
I was just like, "You guys." I turned
around and walked out. And then the next
day,
they were all bitching
because the station chief,
after the fact, had found some obscure
rule
that unless you are conducting an
operational meeting
they won't pay for alcohol.
So, people are ordering these $20, you
know,
espresso martinis
multiple espresso martinis and
everybody's out of pocket $100 because
that wasn't an operational meeting.
You're just hoping that somebody from
that delegation happens to walk into the
bar
and sit and order drink and then you,
you know, you all beat each other up to
see who can talk about conversation with
a guy. Oh man, I was so glad I didn't
stay.
Bunch of bums.
>> To be fair, they did tell you to go to
the bar.
>> They did. It was bad leadership is what
it was.
>> And something else you mentioned when
you were talking about the use the
example of like running an SDR on China
like eight-hour SDR with infrared
cameras and
it just got me thinking like you you
mentioned this very briefly. We kind of
ran out of time in our last interview
where you said something along the lines
of like, you know, gone are the days of
just being able to cross borders and
alias and do a brush pass because
>> with with facial recognition software
and AI. I actually posed this question
to a current CIA officer. I said, how do
you guys cross borders? How do you get
through airports? Like in different in
different names and he said, we
don't know yet.
Still struggling. Yeah, the technology
is developing so quickly. They just
can't keep up with it.
>> So,
man, that that a lot of things are
running through my head right now, but
something I just thought of, I heard
from one of the science and technology
people I gave an interview that the
agency is involved in or dabbling in VR
and AR type stuff.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> She didn't want us She didn't say what.
But what would you like what would you
imagine that that's about?
>> Oh man.
Um I don't know cuz I've been out a long
time, but I will tell you that the DS&T
sorry, the the Directorate of Science
and Technology, which is one of the four
directorates at the CIA.
When I was there, it was almost an
afterthought because mostly what it was
responsible for was disguises
and um
you know, briefcases with secret pockets
in them and you know, supporting
operations. Now, they are so
sophisticated
and so far advanced working with the
likes of Palantir
and Elon Musk's different companies and
AWS and all these like cutting-edge, you
know, Nvidia, all these cutting-edge
tech companies. They are so far advanced
that instead of doing the silly
concealment devices and disguises,
they just pawn that off to, you know,
to, you know, individuals or
or makeup companies and
and and they do the big ticket items
now. I would say what the DS&T is doing
with things like virtual reality
are closer now to what DARPA is doing on
futuristic tech than what they ever did
in the past at the CIA.
>> So, what would you say as an example,
like what would a big ticket item be in
that case?
>> Man, I you know what? I I couldn't even
venture to say it. I I don't even know.
It's become so sophisticated. I sat next
to a guy for years.
Awesome guy, terrific analyst.
And he always had a thing for tech.
We used to joke about it cuz we were all
young, we were all in our 20s, we're all
tech-savvy. Now,
he's the CIA's Chief Technical Officer.
SIS 4.
He could be the director if the
president wanted him to be.
And I remember saying to a buddy of mine
when when our friend was promoted, I was
like, "Man, he really made it like to
the very top." And my friend said, "It
was It was the tech."
You know, he
I'll tell I'll tell you what he did.
Just as a favor on his day off.
Um he made a computer program
to allow
our
Middle East analysts
to make family trees of the royal
families in the countries that they
cover. Right? No such software existed.
There was no such thing as, you know,
family tree maker or genealogy.com.
There was no such thing as .com. I mean,
we're talking about pre-internet days.
And he took 3 days off on his own time
and made this program the software that
everybody in the office used. And I was
like, "Wow, he really knows a lot about
tech, huh?"
And then two or three years later, they
invented the internet or they didn't
invent it then, but they they released
the internet to the general public.
And he just jumped right in and really
really made something out of himself.
So, he's in charge of all this stuff
now.
Yeah.
>> Did you ever have an experience with
DARPA?
>> Never. I was never cleared to even know
what it was they were doing over there.
They're so far advanced.
>> Right. And that's what they say. They
say uh they say DARPA's 20 years ahead
of what we can see.
>> Mhm.
>> And so I would think that
is the agency?
>> Yeah.
One of the things I learned early on in
the agency though is that it is
far cheaper and far easier to just buy
something that's already been invented
than it is to develop it from scratch.
That was before 9/11. Post 9/11, money's
not an issue
at all.
And so DARPA's doing it, NSA's doing it,
CIA's doing it. And then they're with
with In-Q-Tel, they're financing it
uh in the public sector. I'm sorry, in
the private sector.
So,
the sky's the limit, man.
It really is. I can't even imagine the
Russians spending that kind of money on
tech. Maybe the Chinese do, I don't
know. They've got the money.
But since 9/11,
we've gone
we've gone whole hog
in tech development.
>> Chinese could always just steal it from
us, I guess, right?
>> it from us. Yeah. Yeah, just like the
Israelis do.
>> We'll talk about that.
>> Don't get me started. Oh, we'll talk
about the Mossad.
>> Mossad. Don't worry. Um,
In-Q-Tel is the the it's openly the
CIA's venture capital firm, right?
>> Correct. Yeah.
>> And they're I want to say invest they
invested in Palantir or
>> They gave Palantir their first
it was like a million and a half to get
off the ground.
Very first investment. And now look at
Palantir.
Just this year for the first time they
have more than a billion dollars in
revenue.
So, it's it's a success story.
>> So, Palantir does commercial stuff now,
too. It's not just
DOD and government contracts.
>> It's a stand-alone profitable tech
company.
>> Right. So, they're selling to civilians,
so to speak. But, um, I remember when I
remember hearing when Palantir first
came out that people at the agency
didn't like it.
>> At all.
>> And maybe they gave them a trial run or
something. They were like, "Fuck this.
We don't want to use this." Do they use
it now, you think?
>> Yeah.
>> What is it What would they use it for?
>> Oh, all kinds of stuff. Mostly
Well,
I you know what, I probably shouldn't
say.
I probably shouldn't say.
>> Would it be along the lines of
targeting?
>> Yes.
Yes.
You know, this this metadata has to come
from somewhere.
Right? So, like with I was a beta. And
remember, I was a beta was 23
years ago.
Where we're just laying out papers on
the ground and trying to connect the
dots. It's way more sophisticated now.
You can't get away now. You just can't
get away.
So,
rather than have
analysts pouring over this stuff and you
just hoping that your analysts are
really, really smart.
AI does it all.
They do all of it.
And it makes it much easier. That's why,
you know, that's why in the Obama
administration, John Brennan had the
Tuesday morning kill list meetings.
Because the tech got sophisticated
enough that you could just write up a
list of people that you want to kill
that week.
And you
dish out the assignments.
The teams go out, they kill everybody
that's on the list, and then they meet
next Tuesday. And get that kill list.
And you just do it week after week.
Well, if you're not having to devote
armies of targeting analysts
uh to to finding these guys, if if your
computers can find them just based on
their, you know,
email messaging, text messaging,
whatever, metadata.
There.
Your job's easy.
You just fire a missile from the drone
or you drop a guy in that does a
close-in shot.
And then you get back on the helicopter
and fly home.
I hate to sound cynical like that, but
that's just the way it is.
>> I think that's uh
just calling it how it is.
What uh what year or years was that was
Brennan doing that Tuesday morning kill
list?
>> He started in '09
and kept it going. I have no idea if
Donald Trump kept it
or Joe Biden kept it or revived it. But
it was something that they were very
proud of in the Obama administration.
They were just going out whacking
everybody.
>> Yeah, well, no but nobody
dropped more missiles from drones than
Obama did.
>> No, nobody. Nobody. And you know,
somebody said, I I naively said, you
know, the oversight committees need to
be on this. And then a friend of mine
said
to say what in their re-election
campaigns? We need to kill fewer
terrorists.
If I'm re-elected
>> That'll be a good one.
>> America in the 21st century.
>> And you and you and John Brennan are not
the biggest fans of each other, right?
>> No, sir.
>> Why not?
>> John and I have always hated each other.
I never liked him. I never trusted him.
I believe that he is the archetypal
sociopath.
Somebody just by dint of his sociopathy
has been able to rise to the top.
Yeah.
And we go back to 1990. I mean, I've
known John for what What is that now? 35
years. Never liked him. Never trusted
him. Never respected him.
But he had a rabbi in George Tenet.
And
and the next thing you know, he's at the
top of the heap. It was John Brennan who
literally
put me in prison.
John had a
John had a Nixonian obsession with
national security leaks
except when he was the one doing the
leaking.
And now it's come back to bite him in
the ass.
Uh and we can get into that if you want,
but
after I blew the whistle on the torture
program
um and John became the Deputy National
Security Advisor for counterterrorism in
Obama's first term. He went on to be CIA
Director in the second term.
John asked the Justice Department to
secretly reopen the case against me. The
Bush administration said I had not
committed a crime. They closed the case.
I had no idea that my phones were
tapped, my emails were intercepted, FBI
guys following me everywhere.
And then John wrote
a memo to Eric Holder, who was the uh
Attorney General at the time. And he
said, "Charge him with espionage."
And Holder wrote back and said, "My
people don't think he committed
espionage."
And then,
Brennan wrote back and said, "Charge him
anyway and make him defend himself."
So, they arrested me, charged me with
five felonies, three counts of
espionage, waited until I went bankrupt,
and then dropped the espionage charges.
So, I ended up taking a plea to a lesser
charge. I did 23 months in prison. And
and it was because I had revealed the
CIA's dirty laundry and this illegal,
immoral torture program.
And now it's John's turn to be on the
hot seat.
John and all his cronies like Jim
Clapper and Jim Comey
and Hillary Clinton
and all these other ones who thought
they were untouchable,
now they're going to have to answer for
their actions.
>> So, before we come back to that, uh I
think it was in 2005,
Brennan was appointed CEO of a company
called The Analysis Corporation.
>> Mhm.
>> Wasn't this the company that was stood
up for senior intelligence service
officers to use as like a tax
pass-through before they went to [__]
Pizzagate?
>> one of two.
Um The Analysis Company was one. It was
based in in Arlington, Virginia. And the
other was called um
Abraxas Corporation.
It's funny because The Analysis Company
was where all the SIS, Senior
Intelligence Service level
analysts would go, the retired analysts.
And Abraxas was where the retired ops
guys would go. And they were
legitimately set up just as LLC
pass-throughs, right? So, people could
go smoke cigars and drink coffee and
tell stories with their friends and hang
out all day.
And then, lo and behold,
they started making money
after 9/11. Abraxas was bought by I
think it was IBM for
well over a billion dollars. All these
guys got not just rich, but they got
like, you know,
Mega Millions Lotto kind of rich.
And then
And then the the analysis company, it's
funny, you know, everybody
it seems like everybody who's left the
Directorate of Intelligence has tried to
do private intelligence, either as a
singleton or working for one of these
these companies. And it never succeeds.
Right? Cuz pretty much anybody can do
analysis if you're an expert enough in
in a in a topic. So, why would you pay
millions of dollars for these CIA
cronies to
to write you a paper
when you can just hire some professor
and give him five grand and he can do it
for you. He's as much an expert as they
are. Cuz they don't have access to
classified information anymore. And even
if they did, they couldn't give it to
you.
So, it didn't work. He was also on the
board of
It was like BAE Systems and there were a
couple of Beltway Bandits and defense
contractors.
You know, 60,000 here, 100,000 there.
And you put together a pretty good
living.
>> Mhm. So, can you explain to people what
private intelligence is?
>> Oh, sure. I actually did it for for
several years.
Um
Private intelligence really is is what
it sounds like. You're doing exactly
what you did at the CIA, whether it's
analysis or operations, you're just not
using classified information to do it.
And I'll give you an example.
Um
I got a call from a Cypriot billionaire
one time.
And
he said that
he had one daughter, just one daughter,
who was going to inherit all of his
wealth, and she was engaged to this bum,
this Greek Cypriot guy who lived in
London.
And he said, "I don't like this guy. I
don't want this guy anywhere near my
money or my daughter, and I need for you
to find out as much about him as you
possibly can."
And I said, "Okay. So,
uh what's my budget?"
And he gave me a number. I flew to
Cyprus. I
I bribed a police captain
uh to to give me
all the secret police files.
I flew to London. I did surveillance on
this guy's building.
And finally, it took me about 6 weeks
of working full-time. And I I got back
to the billionaire, and I said, "Yeah,
he's a bum, and he's cheating on her."
So, I said,
"First of all, he's been stealing money
from her.
And he used the money to buy some
warehouse in London, and I had satellite
pictures of it from Google Earth
or Google, yeah, Earth. And uh I said,
"He's gone in
with with some partners. There's like an
Armenian guy and a Turkish guy, and they
all went in. They're losing money, but
they used your money, I said, to buy the
place.
He told your daughter it was for
something else, and then he just took
the money and bought this warehouse. So,
that money's gone. He's trying to buy a
mansion in London because he thinks as
soon as he gets married, he's going to
live happily ever after. It's all about
the money."
And I said, "And besides that, he has
multiple drug arrests." He's like,
"What?"
And I said, "Yeah, he
smuggling.
He was smuggling drugs from Israel into
Cyprus. He got caught,
got arrested, paid off some judge, so he
was never prosecuted. Um the Brits think
that he's smuggling drugs there.
So, the old man went to his daughter,
and he he told her,
"You're being scammed." So, that's
operationally private intelligence.
Private analysis is different. It's
actually a lot more fun.
So, I went into business for myself
in the years between when I left
Deloitte & Touche or the year and a half
between when I left Deloitte & Touche
and I went to the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee. And I picked it up
again when I left the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee. So, one of my big I
I had three big clients. I had
the ninth largest mutual sorry, the
ninth largest
hedge fund in the world. I had a mutual
fund and I had
the largest
mining company in the world.
And then I did I did a contract for an
oil company as well. So, they would ask
very, very specific questions.
Who's going to win the Romanian
municipal elections in September?
I'm like, "Ay, ay, ay. I don't know
anything about Romania. So, where do you
go? You go to LinkedIn, right?" I'm
Orthodox
and everybody in Romania is Orthodox.
So, I send connection requests to every
every body who looks interesting, who
happens to be Orthodox in Romania. It's
like 60 people and I say, "Hey, I got
this question, you know?"
One guy gave me private polling data.
So, I said to the client and I said, "It
would help me
in the in the analysis, it would help me
if I knew
why you cared who is going to win the
municipal election." And they said,
"Sure.
We're thinking of buying a silver mine
and the silver mine is underneath a
village.
And to mine the silver, we have to
destroy the whole village.
So, if the socialists win, they're not
going to let us do it.
And if the conservatives win, they'll
just relocate everybody and we'll just
destroy the thing and take the silver."
And I said, "Well, the polls say the
conservatives are going to win." And so,
they bought the mine at the pre-election
price. The conservatives win, they move
everybody out of the village, the
company destroys the village and takes
out billions of dollars worth of silver.
Another one was This one was kind of
funny.
Ayayay, this company
they buy an oil field
um or they they didn't buy it, they
leased an oil field, but they leased it
for like 99 years
in Oman.
And it's right on the border with Yemen.
And none of them had any idea
at the time that Al-Qaeda controls the
border of Oman and Yemen. And you're not
going to be able to get anywhere near
that oil, not within 50 miles of it.
So they they wanted to know
um if the Omanis if they approached the
Omanis and offered to pay
for the Omani military to force Al-Qaeda
out, would the Omanis do it?
Or should they just walk away from this
oil lease?
So I went to Oman, I talked to the
Minister of Oil, and the Deputy Minister
of Oil, I talked to the Deputy uh
Intelligence Service Director, and I I
kind of knew all these guys. Like we had
met, we weren't like buddies or
anything, but we had met. So when I
asked for the appointment through the
Omani Embassy, they said, "Yes, yes,
come and come and you know, we'll have a
conversation." So I went back to the
company and I said
I said, "They're going to gouge you,
but they'll push Al-Qaeda out of your
oil field."
And so they were able to drill for the
oil.
That's what private intelligence is.
>> So when you tell stories in that
context, it just it it makes it seem
like you're
That makes it seem you're like a
high-speed private investigator.
>> That's really what it comes down to.
Yes.
>> Are you familiar with Black Cube?
>> No.
Nope, don't know that one.
>> They're uh
They're a private intelligence firm that
is staffed by uh they're an Israeli
private intelligence firm that is all
ex-Mossad guys. Um
and they allegedly uh I think David
Boies is the head attorney on the
Epstein
>> Oh, sure.
>> Allegedly David Boies used it on
someone.
>> See, the Israelis have no compunction at
all about violating any law that gets in
their way.
And then they say, "What are you going
to do about it?"
>> Yeah. Uh
we'll get there in a second cuz I want
to I want to ask you so you mentioned um
private intelligence. You're not using
classified information to do it is what
you said.
>> Right.
>> Um but what about what about when the
agency
works with private intelligence firms?
Because I I read um Leon Panetta's book,
who was CIA director in the Obama
administration as well as Secretary of
Defense.
But he he mentions um
he starts talking about he's like one of
the first things I did was shut down
this program that was I forget how he
described it, either controversial or
unnecessary or something like that, but
he gave no detail. And I was like, "What
the hell's he talking about?"
So, I look it up and it was the it was a
Blackwater assassination program to go
after targets globally. And long story
short, he ended up outing Erik Prince to
uh the House Intelligence Committee by
name. Erik Prince was operating, I
guess, as a non-credited 201 file.
>> That's why Erik Prince lives in Dubai
now and not in the United States.
>> So, I guess my my question to you then
is like I had no idea and also
Blackwater was involved in stealing
secrets. Like they had a network of
spies. When you think about Blackwater,
do you think about boots on the ground,
military contracts? People know that
they ran the GRS program for CIA, but
like what how how did how would a CIA
how would the CIA work with a contractor
like that?
>> The first thing you do
is the contractor appoints all former
CIA people to its board of directors.
And then you make the former head of the
Counterterrorism Center, Cofer Black,
your vice president.
And then you hire all of Cofer's buddies
to be the head of your different
divisions.
So,
is it CIA? Not really. It's quasi CIA.
Everybody's from the CIA. Everybody's
getting rich, right? Because remember
post 9/11, money was literally not an
issue.
I I told you in our last conversation
that I don't know, four, five, six days
after 9/11, I went up to Cofer Black,
again, the head of the CIA's
Counterterrorism Center, and I said,
"Cofer, I have an idea for an operation
I want to pass by you." And he put up
his hands and he says, "Whatever it is,
just do it. I have so much money I can't
possibly spend it all."
And so I did it.
So,
you know, when when Erik Prince goes to
the CIA and says, "Yeah, I'll do all
these things for you. We've got
assassination squads, we've got
interceptors, we've got boots on the
ground, we'll do anything you want. I
want a billion and a half dollars." And
then the CIA wires it the next day.
Then you can do whatever you want. But
the thing is, is how do you control
people who don't actually work for you?
You can't.
And you risk them going rogue, which of
course they do, because it's their
nature.
If you're being If you're being
contracted to run an assassination
program,
you're going to go out there and
assassinate people.
Well, everybody's human and you make
mistakes.
And you convince yourself that, you
know, Ahmed Schmahmaed is a really bad
guy.
And actually, nah, it's a cousin with a
similar name, but you just put a bullet
in this guy's head. Uh okay. You write a
check for 100 grand to his widow and
just move on.
And that's not cool. It's a It's a
crime. You can't just go around
murdering people because you think they
might be a bad guy.
And so Panetta, I never really liked
Panetta. Just cuz he's not a nice guy.
But um but Panetta was right to shut
that down.
>> Okay, so um
what are the what are the legalities
then
of a
Blackwater team going out to hit
somebody as if a ground branch team
would. It's Is it like I think Title 10,
Title 50.
>> Right.
>> One's military, one's CIA. Can't
remember which was which.
>> Actually, the 9th Circuit Court of
Appeals just ruled on this. I'm going to
say 3 weeks ago, 4 weeks ago.
Um because that's that's a legitimate
legal question that you're asking. What
it What are the legalities? It's never
been tried before.
Right?
Like the CIA has
permission through the amended version
of Executive Order 12333
to kill anybody in the world who poses a
clear and present danger to the United
States.
Okay?
And the CIA is going to decide who's the
clear and present danger. And they're
not going to tell you cuz you're not
cleared, right? I'm not cleared.
You We're just going to have to take
their word for it. But they have the
legal authority to kill people through
12333.
Then they hire these contractors. Like
well, we have GRS, we have we have
ground branch and marine branch and air
branch and we have all these these teams
that are out there killing, kidnapping,
blowing up, you know, whatever.
But they're not agency personnel.
They just work for these private
companies like Blackwater.
So, is that legal?
And the the 9th Circuit Court of Appeals
said, yes, it's legal. So long as they
have a written contract
they are acting on behalf of the CIA and
the CIA has presidential authority to
carry out these operations.
Mhm.
That was just decided. And actually, I
got a call from one of the attorneys in
the case and he said, I have no idea why
nobody in the media gives a [__] about
this decision. And so I I told him I
would write something. But there's
nothing out there. Nobody paid any
attention to this decision.
And it it The reason I paid attention
was because um
it was Abu Zubaydah who was the
plaintiff
in the case. Abu Zubaydah said these
guys tortured me and I want to sue them.
And the court was like, "Yeah, sorry you
got tortured, but they were acting on
behalf of the CIA and the CIA was
legally permitted to torture people, so
you're [__] out of luck."
>> Oh, wow. Okay. There's a lot of places
to go there.
First of all, you you you mentioned that
you went to Cofer with an idea for an
operation. Can you say what that was?
>> It was dumb. Um
Our our orders after 9/11. I mean, in in
the days after 9/11, literally everybody
was working on Al-Qaeda. Everybody in
the counterterrorism center. I'm talking
thousands and thousands of people.
And then, once we got our bearings, I'm
going to say
a couple of weeks after 9/11, we got our
bearings
and
authorities were divided up.
I went back to my home base, which was,
you know, 17 November.
And so
our standing orders from the White House
were to destroy every terrorist group in
the world that meant Americans harm.
And so we started going back through,
you know
35-year-old
files looking for leads
and I found a couple
in the unlikeliest places, like
Switzerland
and Milan.
You know, terrorists get old and retire,
too, as crazy as it sounds. I told you
the story about Bruno, the Sacha Baron
Cohen film.
People get old and they're like, "Eh,
I'm tired of this terrorism stuff. I'm
just going to retire."
>> You didn't tell the story about Bruno.
You told the story What what I thought
of is when you went to that old man who
had who was working on a bank at the
time. He was the one that witnessed the
murder, but you didn't tell the story
about Bruno.
>> I didn't?
>> I I don't think so.
>> I get a call from Sacha Baron Cohen one
night
and he says, "Hey, I don't I don't you
know my characters, but" I said, "Oh,
yeah." I said, "Listen, Borat." I said,
"I almost pissed myself in the theater."
It's still the funniest movie I've ever
seen in my life.
So, he said, "Well, I've got this
character Bruno." I said, "Yeah, yeah,
the the gay Austrian fashion
correspondent." He said, "Yeah." So,
he made me sign a non-disclosure
agreement. And um he said, "Literally
nobody's in on the gag except
um Pam Anderson."
Literally no one else in the film was in
on the gag.
Well, except
uh
that was in Borat, except Borat's
assistant. So, anyway,
um
he said, "We can't let anybody know that
it's me and that I'm in character." And
I said, "Okay, so what can I do for
you?"
And he said,
"We're going to go to the Middle East.
I want to get in front of bonafide
terrorists." he said.
I'm thinking Hezbollah
or Al-Qaeda.
And I want to show them Polaroids of men
having anal sex, like hardcore anal sex.
And I want to ask them if this is a form
of torture and should these men be sent
to Guantanamo."
>> Oh, [__] god.
>> So, I said, I go, "Oh,
that's a
that's a bad idea."
Yeah, and I said, "You know, just as a
general rule,
you really shouldn't mess with the
religious types."
I go, "They'll kill you, they'll kill
your crew, they'll go out onto the
street and kill people who remind them
of you."
And he said, "Well, I've got to make it
totally believable."
So,
so we met a couple of days later and I
said, "I have an idea."
Well, before that he said he wanted to
he wanted to film it in Syria.
And I go, "Yeah, that's that's not a
good idea, either."
And um
I said, "I know
I know the Libyan ambassador
in Washington, and the Libyans are
trying really hard. This is a year
before Gaddafi was killed. I said, "The
Libyans are trying really hard to sort
of, you know, integrate and get with the
program with the West. And, they're
always asking if we know of any films
that might want to film in in Libya."
He said, "Can't do it." He said, "As a
Jew," he said, "I just
I would fear for my safety in Libya. I
can't do it."
And I said, "Well,
I said, "Syria really we shouldn't mess
with, and Lebanon you can't do." I said,
"We could do Morocco. That's easy.
There's all kinds of films in Morocco,
or even Algeria." And he's like, "No, I
I kind of have my heart set on on
Syria." And I said, "Well, I know the
Syrian ambassador. So, let me just raise
it kind of off the record and see what
his reaction is." He goes, "No, no,
there's a Syrian consulate in Newport
Beach, and I'm going to go down there
next week." I I go, "No, no,
let me do what you're paying me to do,
and I'll take care of it."
Couple nights later, I'm laying in bed,
I'm reading a book. It's late, like
11:30. And the phone rings. And I look,
I said to my wife, "It's Sacha Baron
Cohen."
At 11:30 at night. So, I said, "Sacha,
how are you?" And he says,
with that thick British accent he has,
he goes, "I think I [__] up, mate."
And I said, "Oh, don't tell me you went
to that Syrian consulate."
He goes, "Yeah." He went to the Syrian
consulate. He goes in the the first
door.
He goes, "The consular officer sees him,
comes out from behind the bulletproof
glass and says, 'I know who you are, I
know what you do, and you are not
welcome in Syria.'" I said, "Damn it.
Okay." I said, "We have to figure
something else out." So, then I went to
meet with him.
So, I said, when I got there, "I have an
idea.
I said, "I I strongly that we should
stay away from the religious types.
But, there are bonafide terrorists,
almost all of whom are in Damascus, who
have retired.
Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine, PFLP General Command,
Democratic Front for the Liberation of
Palestine, Abu Nidal Organization. I
said these guys were bad guys, like
hijacking airplanes and blowing up
airplanes and shooting up airports and
working with Carlos the Jackal. I mean,
these were bad guys.
And he said, "Well, how do you get a get
a hold of them?"
And I said,
"I'm going to guess
that they're listed in the Damascus
telephone book."
So, I went to the Library of Congress.
Of course, the Damascus telephone book
is in Arabic.
I go to the Library of Congress. They
have a copy of the Damascus telephone
book. And I find four of these guys.
They're all like in their 70s and they
don't do anything anymore. They just
they're just retired. They drink coffee
and smoke cigarettes and pass the day.
So, I called them.
And I said, "We're doing a documentary
about the Middle East peace process and
about the role of, you know, freedom
fighters and activists." And I made all
this [__] up.
And they said, "Yeah, that they would be
interested in appearing in a documentary
like that." So, I called Sacha and I
said,
"Bingo, we got four of them." And he
"Okay, well, now we have to find a place
to film."
He said, "How about Amman?" I said,
"Amman's a great idea, but
I said, "The Jordanian Intelligence
Service is one of the best in the world.
And they're going to be on you like
white on rice. So, we have to bring the
Jordanians in on the gag."
He said, "Absolutely not.
The Jordanians can't know that it's him
and that it's a comedy.
They have to believe that this is a
legitimate documentary being done by an
Austrian journalist." I said, "Man, this
is a bad idea."
I said, "Sacha, look at it this way.
If the Jordanian intelligence service
sees four bonafide terrorists
all flying to Amman on the same day
to go to your hotel room
you're done.
And he said, "I'm going to have to risk
it. Nobody can be in on the gag."
So,
he and a cameraman flew to Amman the day
before I did.
And
he told me the next day when I arrived,
they land and they get off the plane and
they're walking out like to get a cab,
and there's a guy standing there with a
sign and it says Sacha Baron Cohen.
And And so he says, "I'm Sacha Baron
Cohen." And the guy says, "Oh, the car
is waiting for you."
So, he goes out and there's this limo
and they get in the car
and he says to the cameraman,
"John got us a limo."
I'm not a freaking secretary. I didn't
get him a limo.
So,
they're driving through Amman and he
said it occurred to him that maybe John
didn't get him a limo.
So, he says to the driver,
"Where are we going?"
And the driver says, "The Royal Palace.
His Majesty is a huge fan."
And he said, "These enormous iron gates
open up and they pull into the Royal
Palace grounds and here's the king."
And he's standing with the director of
the Jordanian intelligence service.
So, he gets out of the car and the king
says, "Sacha Baron Cohen, I am your
biggest fan." He said, "Borat, genius. I
didn't think I could make it through."
He said, "Anything that you need while
you're in Jordan,
you talk to this man. He's the head of
the Jordanian intelligence service.
He'll take care of anything you want."
And I said, "I told you. You hadn't even
landed in the country
and they knew that you were doing this.
That's how good they are. So, they were
blown, the cover was blown.
Then they go to the hotel.
So,
the plan was
to get these guys into a room,
show them the Polaroids,
and he wanted them to lunge across the
table to strangle him, to beat him.
So,
I'm sitting behind the camera.
He's at the table interviewing these
guys.
And he's very effeminate in this
character. So, he pulls out the the
Polaroids. And again, these are like
hardcore gay, you know, anal
Polaroids.
And he lays them out.
And uh
he says, "Is this torture? Do these men
they're torturing each other? Should
they be sent to Guantanamo?" And these
guys are old, so they're like they have
their their trifocals on and they're
like one of them picks it up and he goes
like this. He goes,
"Oh,
not good.
This haram.
Not good."
And the other one he hands it to the
other one,
"Ah, no, no, no.
This not good."
And they just set it down.
And they just look at him.
Like, "Damn it.
Nothing's happening."
So, I'm waiting and the cameraman told
me beforehand, "If they react and they
lunge at him,
don't move cuz we want the fight on
camera."
And then they're like, you know,
looking around, light up another
cigarette.
He brings out more pictures. They were
like,
"This not Islam.
Not good."
And then that was it.
So, we finished the scene
and the guys leave. He paid them. I
think he gave them like a hundred
dollars each. And um and I said, "Well,
that was a bust."
And he goes, "Yeah, they didn't they
didn't give a shit."
Uh I said, "No." Cut the entire Jordan
part out of the movie, the entire thing.
And then, ironically,
they went to Jerusalem, I flew home.
It was in Jerusalem
that
Yeshiva students beat the [__] out of
him.
And it was the only time in filming that
he dropped character. He went to the to
the Western Wall, you know, like the
holiest site in all of Judaism.
And he was wearing a leather vest with
no shirt, and he's hairy like a gorilla,
right? So, he's got this leather vest
with no shirt. He has pink hot pants,
like ladies hot pants, and leather boots
that come up over his knee. And he goes
to the Western Wall like this. And this
rabbi saw him, and then the Yeshiva
students were just on him. They beat the
[__] out of him. He had black eyes, his
face was swollen. They had to stop
filming for a week for the for the
swelling to go down.
And he's on the ground, they're kicking
him, they're stomping him, and he he was
saying, "I'm an actor, I'm an actor.
It's just a joke, we're filming a
movie." They didn't care.
They didn't care if it was a joke, and
he was an actor.
>> No, you you mess around in certain parts
of the world, and
>> It was daring and gutsy, and I've said
in in previous interviews, I concluded
that the guy was a genius, and I don't
use the term lightly. He was a genius, a
comic genius. First of all, who would
think of of something like this? Even if
it didn't work in Jordan, who would even
think of something like this?
And then, you know, you go back to
Borat.
And it really holds its comedy. It
really Who would think to do that?
Where there are governments
issuing condemnations
of of a movie.
You know, he's driving past the
the embassy of Uzbekistan, and he's
like, "Fuck you, Uzbekistan!" And they
take out a full-page ad in the
Washington Washington Post. They say,
"We condemn this film. We're proud
people of Uzbekistan. Come on."
>> Genius.
>> You can't not laugh.
>> No way.
>> So, what makes the Jordanians so good?
>> Uh the net the necessity to survive.
Fully 50% of the population of Jordan is
Palestinian. They are Palestinian
refugees and the descendants of
refugees. And we know that because if
you're Jordanian, your passport is
green. And if you're Palestinian, your
passport is black.
And never the two shall meet.
So, in 1968,
there was a Palestinian uh terrorist
group called Black September.
And their goal was to overthrow the
Jordanian monarchy and make Jordan the
new Palestine.
They were fighting literally on the
steps of the palace.
That's how close they got. And the
Jordanians were able to beat them back.
And the Jordanians don't want any more
trouble.
And so,
they had to develop
arguably
the best or second best intelligence
service in the Middle East
just to protect themselves.
We train them, Mossad trains them, the
Saudis train them, and I mean, they're
they're great.
Truly great.
Yeah.
>> Is there anything that stands out that
they're really good out as far as like
are they really good at ops or analysis
or they just well-rounded?
>> They don't even so much care about the
analysis. It's all about ops.
You know, look at it this way. They've
got They've got all these factions, all
these Palestinian factions,
on top of having the the PA, the
Palestinian Authority, and Hamas with
representatives there. And every other
Palestinian group with representatives
there. You know, the Quds Force and you
know, this one and that one and Islamic
Jihad and everybody's there.
And they have to
allow
a simmer
because everybody's going be bitching
about the Israelis.
But they can't let that simmer turn into
a boil that actually presents a threat
to their own stability. So, it's a
constant balancing act. And the only way
that you're able to pull off a balancing
act like that is to infiltrate every one
of these groups.
Mhm. And then you really need the
economy to be good enough
so that
hungry people don't get angry.
>> Did you ever does the CIA do joint ops
with the Jordanians?
>> That's That's a question that I'm not
permitted to answer.
I will say I was at a facility once
at a facility once with the Jordanians
and um
it was in a very, very rural area of the
United States.
And uh
I'm standing with There was a captain
from the Jordanian intelligence service.
And a And a deer walked by.
And he says to me
Hadha ghazal? Is that a gazelle?
And And the funny thing is they only
have gazelles in the Middle East. So,
any kind of deer is a gazelle
in Arabic. So, I said, "Yeah,
it's a it's a gazelle." I said, "We have
millions of them here, too many."
He says
Is tasty?
I said, "Oh, yeah. Makes a nice Makes a
nice stew."
So, I mentioned to the to the lead guy,
I said, "I I think maybe we should shoot
one of these deer."
So, I think these I think the the
Jordanians want to want to eat one. And
he goes, "Cool."
5 minutes later you hear